Brandt, Thomas O.; Papers ger001
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Thomas O. Brandt Papers
1906-1971
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ger001
2.0 cubic ft.
This collection contains biographical materials, correspondence with publishers, 1958-1966, hand-corrected manuscripts of published and unpublished novels including "Stern in Nebel,"which concerns the 1933-1938 period), short stories, essays, literary criticism, children's literature, and poetry, 1947-68, and offprints of journal, magazine, and newspaper articles.
Biographical / Historical
Thomas O. Brandt was born on November 18, 1906, in Vienna, Austria. After completing his doctoral degree in Germanic and English languages and literatures in 1933 at the University of Vienna, he worked in Vienna as a freelance writer, editor, critic and lecturer. His publications included Der Ewige Kreis, an anthology of modern Austrian poetry, and Der Froehliche Gasthof, a novel.
In 1938, Brandt emigrated to the United States and found a position as a research assistant in German Literature at Harvard University. From 1939-1943, he served as Senior Master at the Lakeside Preparatory School in Seattle, Washington. He married Esther L. Myhre (Heidi) in 1942 and became a U.S. citizen in 1943. The birth of sons Christopher (1943), Andrew (1946) and Peter (1947) followed. From 1943-1944, Brandt was a German instructor at Oregon State College and then professor and department chair at William and Mary College from 1945-1947. He spent 1944-1945 working for the U.S. Office of War Information, first as a field representative and editorial assistant in London, and then as editor and chief of the German translation section in New York.
From 1947 to 1966 Brandt taught German at Colorado College where he eventually became full professor and Chair of the Department of German and Russian. There he initiated several foreign student and teaching exchange programs and founded the Max Kade Deutsches Haus. From 1967 to 1968, the year of his death, Brandt was a professor of German at the University of New Hampshire at Durham.
Brandt had a diverse and active career. From the mid 1950s to the late 1960s, he presented many lectures on topics related to Germanic studies and American culture as experienced by Europeans, including a lecture series funded by the U.S. Department of State (1957, 1965) and one at the Goethe Institut in Mexico City (1966). Both series included lectures broadcast on local radio stations. In 1954 and 1956, he led American graduate study groups in Europe and, in 1961, he was invited by the government of the Federal Republic to lead a study tour through Germany. He spent 1956-1957 on a leave of absence from Colorado College as a visiting professor for the University of Maryland in Stuttgart, where he published several articles in the Stuttgarter Zeitung. Brandt also taught at Middlebury College (Vermont), Deutsche Sommerschule during the summers of 1960 and 1962. While on sabbatical in 1963, Brandt travelled to Spain, Mallorca, France, Switzerland and Germany, where he continued his writing. On a leave of absence in 1965, he travelled and lectured in Europe and was a participant in the Internationaler Germanisten Kongress in Amsterdam.
In addition to fulfilling his duties as a professor, Brandt held several offices in various Germanic studies organizations. He served as President of the Mountain-Plains Chapter of the American Association of Teachers of German (1955-1957) and was a member of the National Advisory Board for Wayne State University's Junior Year Program (1966-1968). From 1963-1968 he was a member of the Editorial Board for Universitas in Stuttgart and also served as Managing Editor for the German Language Quarterly, 1962-1964.
Scope and Contents
The Thomas O. Brandt papers are of interest to researchers of German exile literature, Germanistik (study of German language and literature) and academic and cultural developments in post-war United States and Europe. The collection contains some biographical information on Thomas Brandt, particularly as related to his professional activities and correspondence with students and numerous publishers.
The bulk of the collection consists of copies of Brandt's works dating from his pre-emigration days in Vienna to the time of his death in 1968. Poems, many short stories and essays, vignettes, dramas, articles and reviews, novels, lectures and two books appear in the collection. In addition, there are some offprints of Brandt's journal articles. Also of interest are the notes and annotations by Heidi Brandt, the author's wife, on many of the works throughout the collection. No official documents related to Brandt's position with the Office of War Information (1944-1945) appear in the collection. But one vignette, "Civil Service Goes To War" and a few references in his correspondence deal with Brandt's attempt to gain employment with the government and his impressions of his work there.
Brandt published his work in English and German language academic journals and serials. His articles appear in publications ranging from scholarly journals to newspapers such as the Colorado Springs Free Press, Brandt's "hometown newspaper." His publications demonstrate his active engagement in the academic arena as well as a continuous and thoughtful examination of his environment. In addition to publishing book reviews and scholarly research about German language and literature, he wrote about the need for academics to publish, language acquisition, his observations on the American higher education system, aspects of American culture in contrast to European society, politics and travel.
Brandt was a prolific story writer as well as an essayist. The collection contains copies of Brandt's unpublished novels, including Stern im Nebel, which concerns the 1933-1938 period. Brandt's short stories cover a wide range of topics from the whimsical to the satirical. His works often stem from personal experience. Stories such as "Schatten auf Mallorca" and "Eines Tages in Seville" draw from Brandt's impressions of Spain's cultural and political climate during his travels there.
The poetry found in this collection spans Brandt's entire writing career. In 1960, he published a German/English volume of poetry, Gedichte - Poems, and the children's book, Andy, or When I'm Famous. Both works contain lithographs by Heidi Brandt. His poetry shows influence of the German Romantics; prominent themes are nature, the seasons, childhood, love, and death.
Throughout his career, Brandt remained an active and prolific writer. The largest portion of his correspondence deals with his attempts to get his works published. Letters to and from publishers such as Piper, Otto Walter, Carl Hanser, Claassen, Mohrbooks, Kiepenheuer und Witsch, Hoffmann & Campe, Nymphenburger Verlagshandlung date from 1960-1967 and chiefly discuss publication of the author's short stories, "Vignetten und Skizzen" and the story, "Schatten auf Mallorca." Although Brandt published many of his articles, most of his novels and short stories were not published. There is also some correspondence concerning the publication of Brandt's 1960 German/English volume of poetry (Dyva & Jeppsens Bogtrykkeri, Copenhagen). The letters between Brandt and his former students and colleagues from the Lakeside Preparatory School exchanged during WWII show him to be a well-respected and dedicated teacher.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series. Each is arranged chronologically.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Heidi Brandt donated all materials to the M.E. Grenander Department of Speical Collections and Archives in October 1993.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Brandt, Thomas O., 1906-1968; Correspondence; Manuscripts for publication
- Biographical Material, 1906-1968; 2 folders
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  Contains several curriculum vitae, lists of publications and works from 1944 to 1967, newspaper clippings and articles about Brandt and reviews of his publications.
  - Vitae; lists of publications and works, 1906-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings and reviews about Brandt and his publications., 1960-1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1939-1967; 3 folders
  Contains one folder of correspondence from former students and colleagues from the Lakeside Academy during the World War II period (1939-1945). This folder also includes a few letters written by Brandt and one letter about the author written by Brandt's wife after his death (German). The bulk of the correspondence (two folders) deals with Brandt's efforts to get his works published (1958-1966).
  - Letters from students and colleagues, includes 1 letter by Heidi Brandt, 1939-1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters to and from publishers, 1958-1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters from publishers, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Literary Works, 1930-1971
  Arranged chronologically by format.
  This series contains clippings and offprints of articles on Austrian literature and culture, and literature from other German-speaking populations; and book reviews by Brandt from his Vienna days and American career; 49 English and German essays spanning Brandt's career, published and unpublished, about a variety of topics concerning cultural and political issues as well as issues in academia; manuscripts of five of Brandt's unpublished novels, including the three part work, Stern im Nebel; a series of 36 vignettes in German, except for "Civil Service Goes To War," an account of Brandt's Office of War Information (OWI) employment; 914 aphorisms developed by Brandt; 28 largely unpublished short stories in English and German; seven short dramas, including "Gestern Kommt Morgen;" and numerous poems, published and unpublished, written throughout Brandt's career.
  - Articles: 1930s, Vienna, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Articles: Post Vienna Period, 1940-early 1950s, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Articles: 1950s, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Articles: 1960s, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Essays: List, German/English, circa 1935-1951, List, German essays after 1958 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Essays: "Publish or Perish", Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Essays: "The German Study Tour", Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Essays: "Jedermann in der Weltliteratur", 1933-1943 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Essays: "Ibsen und das Wienner Theater", 1933-1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Essays: "Educational Inflation", 1946 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Essays: "Educational Objectives", 1948 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Essays: "On Insincerity in the Arts", 1948 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Essays: "Oesterreichische Dichtung Zwischen Zwei Kriegen", 1949 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Essays: "Austrian Literature Between Two Wars (1918-1938)", 1949 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Essays: "Bemerkungen ueber das Amerikanische Erziehungssystem", 1949 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Essays: "Educational Deflation", 1951 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Essays: "The Modern German Kurzgeschichte", 1951 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Essays: "Aus Den Tellurischen Provinzen und Humor", 1951 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Essays: "American Misconceptions About Modern German Literature", 1953 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Essays: "Versuch Einer Stilldiagnose Unserer Zeit", 1958 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Essays: "Erziehung Als Vernunftglaube", 1958 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Essays: "Sprachautomation in USA", 1958 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Essays: "Anpassung und Unabhaengigkeit in Heutigen Amerika", 1958 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Essays: "Die Krise der Amerikanischen Erziehung", 1958 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Essays: "Cocktails", 1958 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Essays: "Colorado: Traumland der Amerikaner", 1958 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Essays: "Ad Astra", 1958 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Essays: "Gedanken ueber die Zeitengenoessische Deutsche Dichtung", 1959 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Essays: "Die Invasion des Privaten durch die Mechanisierte Sprache", 1955-1965 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Essays: "Parlando--Selbstentfremdung und Unverbindlichkeit", 1955-1965 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Essays: "Elisabeth Langaesser: Gedichte", 1960 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Essays: "A General Statement", 1960 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Essays: "Der Gottesbegriff in der Neueren Deutschen Lyrik", 1960 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Essays: "Epistola Ad Me Ipsum", 1960 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Essays: "Amerikanismen", 1960 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Essays: "Machtspiel und Unermuedbarkeit der Amerikanischen Reklame", 1960 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Essays: "Amerikanische Eindruecke von einer Studienreise", 1961 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Essays: "Hitler Ante Portas", 1961 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Essays: "Brecht und die Bibel", 1962 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Essays: "Portugesisches Ballett", 1963 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Essays: "Einsamkeit in Amerika", 1963 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Essays: "Versuch ueber den Nordamerikanischen Humor", 1963 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Essays: "Freiheit in USA", 1963 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Essays: "Lyrik Ohne Leier", 1964 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Essays: "Die Amerikanische Germanistik und Ihre Zeitschriften", 1964 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Essays: "Rhetorik in den Vereinigten Staaten", 1964 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Essays: "Bertolt Brechts Amerikabild", 1964 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Essays: "Die Sprachfuehrung Bertolt Brechts", 1964 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Essays: "Service - Made in USA", 1964 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Essays: "Der Amerikanische Optimismus", 1965 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Essays: "Weltraum fahrt - Wohin?", 1965 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Essays: "Die Zahl als Mythos?", 1965 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Essays: "Die Grossen Debatten Amerikas", 1966 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Essays: "Staatsuniversitaeten im Goldenen Westen", 1966 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Novel: "Die Liebenden,", early work from Vienna period, 1930-1940 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Novel: "Der Mut der Feigheit: ein Kleines Tagebuch aus Grosser Zeit", 1939 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Novel: "Stern im Nebel", Undated (Box 1, Folder 62)
    Notes from author/Heidi Brandt re: novel
  - Novel: "Stern im Nebel," Part I, 1939-1957 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    German
  - Novel: "Stern im Nebel," Parts I-II, 1939-1957 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    German, with notes from the author
  - Novel: "Stern im Nebel," Part II, 1939-1957 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Novel: "Stern im Nebel," Part III, 1939-1957 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Novel: "Stern im Nebel" (Star in the Fog), 1939-1957 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    Author's Summary in English
  - Novel: "Stern im Nebel" (Star in the Fog), Part I, 1939-1957 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    English
  - Novel: "Stern im Nebel" (Star in the Fog), Part II, 1939-1957 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Novel: "Stern im Nebel" (Star in the Fog), Part III, 1939-1957 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Novel: "Heineckes Gast", 1953 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Novel: "Schatten auf Mallorca", 1966 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Vignettes: "Civil Service Goes To War" (work at OWI), 1935-1945 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Vignettes: "Repartee", 1946 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Vignettes: "Das Schoene Maedchen", 1951 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Vignettes: "Das Schiff in der Flasche", 1951 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Vignettes: "Muede", 1951 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Vignettes: "Drei Brueder", 1951 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Vignettes: "Hilarianer Beeren", 1953 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Vignettes: "Der Krieger", 1954 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Vignettes: "Die Fliege", 1956 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Vignettes: Original Lists from Brandt, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Vignettes: "Textuellekonvergenz", 1955-1965 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Vignettes: "Die Tapferkeitsmedaille", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Vignettes: "Am Fenster", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Vignettes: "Llangollen", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Vignettes: "Woroschilow", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Vignettes: "Umzug", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Vignettes: "Jumporama", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Vignettes: "MBA", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Vignettes: "Die Greisen", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Vignettes: "Hitler Ante Portas", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Vignettes: "Der Kaefig", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Vignettes: "Anstandsbesuch", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Vignettes: "Strassenkreuzung", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Vignettes: "Wahlvorgang", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Vignettes: "Von den Moeglichkeiten", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Vignettes: "Auf Besuch", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Vignettes: "Freundlicher Nachbar", Undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Vignettes: "Zeitraumalgebra", 1964 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Vignettes: "Urlaub", 1964 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Vignettes: "Ehre", 1964 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Vignettes: "Spare in der Zeit", 1964 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Vignettes: "Ruhm", 1964 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Vignettes: "Die Rede", 1964 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Vignettes: "Ueber Schnelligkeit", 1964 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Vignettes: "Bescheidenheit Ist Eine Zier", 1964 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Vignettes: "In Der Praerie", 1964 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Vignettes: "Das Waren noch Zeiten", 1964 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Vignettes: "Beschwerliche Nacht", 1964 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Vignettes: "Nicht Umsonst", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Vignettes: "Herr und Diener", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Vignettes: "Meditationen", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Vignettes: "Zitate", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Vignettes: "Alphabetanien", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Vignettes: "Duerfen", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Vignettes: "Eine Verwirrende Begebenheit", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Vignettes: "Tante Luise", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Vignettes: "Wortverfremdung", 1966 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Vignettes: "Philologie", 1966 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Vignettes: "Shine", 1966 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Vignettes: "Schlagwoerter", Undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Vignettes: "Veraenderungen", 1967 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Vignettes: "Wer Immer Strebend Sich Bemueht...", 1967 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Vignettes: "Schadenfreude", 1967 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Vignettes: "Fragebogen", 1967 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Vignettes: "Lehrsaetze", 1967 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - One series collected throughout Brandt's career, Undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Short Stories: Notes on Stories, Undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Short Stories: "Der Heimkehrer", 1951 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Short Stories: "Der Trauergast", 1951 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Short Stories: "KIM", 1951 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Short Stories: "Der Held", 1951 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Short Stories: "Die Schallplatte", 1951 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Short Stories: "Die Hilarianer Beeren", 1953 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Short Stories: "Die Fliege", 1956 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Short Stories: "An Einem Fruehlingsabend", 1957 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Short Stories: "Madeleine", 1958 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Short Stories: "Seltsame Wiederkehr", 1959 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Short Stories: "Einsame Schildkroete", 1959 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Short Stories: "Giuditta", 1959 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Short Stories: "Die Beichte", 1959 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Short Stories: "Die Reise Nach Mexico", 1960 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Short Stories: "Helena in Oregon", 1960 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Short Stories: "IMA", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Short Stories: "Der Fall Oliver", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Short Stories: "Rede Aus Dem Sarg", 1963 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Short Stories: "Eines Tages in Sevilla", 1963 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Short Stories: "Kuehle Leidenschaften", 1963 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Short Stories: "Ein Altes Haus", 1963 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Short Stories: "Die Rechnung", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Short Stories: "Der Fall Oliver", 1960-1970 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Short Stories: "Professor W.", Undated (Box 2, Folder 81)
    File includes one letter from Brandt's Professor (Vienna) and one letter by Heidi Brandt about the story
  - Short Stories: "Campusbesuch", 1967 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Short Stories: "Merkwuerdiges Ende Eines Erfolgreichen Mannes", 1967 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Short Stories: "Capriccio" eighteen Italian stories, 1951-1958 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Drama: "Hochzeit und Heimkehr", Undated (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Drama: "Getsern Kommt Morgen," various editions, 1951-1956 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Drama: "Gestern Kommt Morgen," various editions, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Drama: "Die Reichen und die Armen (Las Rica Y Las Pobres), oder Gleich und Gleich Gestellt sich Gern", 1963 (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Drama: "Los Caballeros Y Sas Seoras", 1963 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Drama: "Schwierigkeiten oder Treu Ist Alles", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Drama: "The Congressman", 1961-1971 (Box 2, Folder 91)
    note from Heidi Brandt
  - Drama: "Freedom and Authority", 1967 (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Poems: Early 1960s, includes: "Epitaph," Brechts Zimmer," "Ein Altes Pergament," "Ost Berlin," and others, Undated (Box 2, Folder 93)
    17 leaves
  - Later Years, 1965-68, includes: "For Chris," "For My Son," "Vietnam," "Kontrast XV," "Virginische Landschaft," "Wind vom Mittelmeer," and others, Undated (Box 2, Folder 94)
    34 leaves